# Robert Whittaker

High-Technology Business Professional

Au Ferrajoz 5
1029 Villars-Ste-Croix
Switzerland
+41 79 406 5747

rwhittaker@ieee.org
Swiss 'C' permit
English, French and German
C. Eng., FEANI Eur.Ing., MIET, MIEEE

# **Profile**

Results-oriented leader and influencer with a high-level technical education and over twenty years of international experience in Business Management, Business Development, International Sales and Marketing and Engineering Management gained with multi-national high-technology companies within Europe and the United States. A clear communicator with a strong organizational ability and can work independently or with a team to meet deadlines and deliver quality results.

# **Professional Experience**

# 2008- MEAS Switzerland SA, Bevaix, Switzerland

Swiss subsidiary of Measurement Specialties, a Nasdaq-listed (MEAS) manufacturer of Industrial Sensors (~2700 employees).

Reporting to the Executive Vice President of the pressure/force sensor group

#### Director of Marketing and & Business Development, Pressure Products

- Ensuring position of market leader in high-performance digital sensing using the combination of engineering skills and business acumen
- Market assessment and new product definition in the focus markets of Medical (US & Europe), Automotive (Germany), Consumer (Asia-Pacific)
- Budget responsibility (revenue, margin, pricing) for MEMS sensing products
- Product line strategy, technology & product roadmaps and five-year plan
- Key-account acquisition and management

#### **Director of Sales**

- Sales responsibility for all products manufactured in Switzerland
- New business development and customer acquisition
- Key account management

## 2002-2007 Semtech SA, Neuchâtel, Switzerland

Nasdaq-listed (SMTC) mixed-signal analogue semiconductor manufacturer

# **Business Unit Manager for Radio Frequency Products**

- Profit & Loss responsibility for a multi-disciplinary team of product development, application support and marketing professionals supporting customers world-wide
- Defined the business rationale for entering the Wireless Sensing Market including business case, market study and definition of a low-power ZigBee / IEEE 802.15.4 SoC
- Business development: developed the product offering for the Automated Meter Reading market in China from market entry to design wins within electricity, gas and water utilities
- Developed new business initiatives (RF modules, mixed-signal components) from business case to product launch and achieved targeted revenue growth in the home automation and industrial controls market segment
- Built and managed multi-discipline applications support team

### **Product Line Manager Wireless Products**

- Marketing Responsibility for a portfolio of radio-frequency products including sales revenue, gross margin and revenue growth
- Product development cycle management

# 2000-2002 Worldzap AG, Zug Switzerland and London

Video content provider joint-venture of Kirch Group, Germany

#### **VP Technology Strategy**

- Architect of content delivery service for premium content services to Wi-Fi enabled terminals and mobile devices (Bundesliga World Ice Hockey, F1 motor racing)
- Business model for software licensing (video compression, rights management) to commercial partners
- Evangelist for time-critical mobile content at industry forums and trade shows
- Worked with Nokia and Packet Video in the elaboration of video-clip content delivery as part of a portfolio of new media subscription services for mobile operators
- Digital rights content implementation based on technologies developed by Intertrust and France Telecom research

### 1989-2000 Philips Electronics, Zürich

Semiconductor division of Europe's largest electronics company. Worked at the Global competence centre for Mobile (GSM) and Cordless (DECT, 900 MHz) telephony

#### 1996 to 2000 International Marketing Manager Cordless Business Line

Marketing of DSP-based and microcontroller telecom solutions to serve a worldwide client-base of multi-national blue-chip manufacturers.

- Budget responsible for a product portfolio (DSP-based products, software, radio products) with an annual sales volume of \$35M (2000)
- Business cases (market analysis, system definition, profitability, planning) for new semiconductor and software solutions – Internet devices, digital answering machines/codecs, caller identification, cordless telephony, digital voice recorders
- Software commercialisation as a product and licensing
- Asia Market Development: grew VTech in China from zero to a \$20-million account over a two-year period (Sales exceeded \$100-million in 2005)
- New Business creation in Hong Kong, Korea, Taiwan, Singapore and Australia
- New Products: defined and launched fifteen products solutions (hardware + software) worldwide via the international sales force, and directed applications support team in the design-in activity. CAGR of 24% achieved as a result in this market sector.

## 1995 to 1996 Marketing Communications Manager, Telecom Products Group (TPG)

Responsible for marketing communications for the three centres (Caen, Nürnberg and Zürich) reporting back to Philips Corporate Marcom at the headquarters in Eindhoven

- Responsible for TPG coordinated world-wide product launches
- Marcom budget responsibility and management
- Documentation
  - Product Launches, Web presence, Electronic documentation
- Events: organized presence at international events (Telecom, Cebit, IFA)

#### 1989 to 1994 Design Manager NV Microcontrollers, Faselec AG

#### 1986 to 1988 Texmate Incorporated, San Diego, CA

Director of Engineering for Instrumentation and measuring products (4-20 mA loop, Wheatstone bridge, temperature, PID controllers)

# **Education**

Further	Courses in Marketing, Supply Chain, Negotiation, Purchasing
1985	Post-Doctoral research in high-speed graphics at Manchester University
1984	PhD by research with industrial sponsorship by Plessey at Manchester University
1981	M.Sc. by research in radar signal simulation at Manchester University
1980	BSc. Honours in Electronic Engineering at Manchester University